A Guide to the Virginia Academy of Science Records, 1920-2005
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Virginia Academy of Science Records, 1920-2005
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms1981-096
60.2 cu. ft. 43 boxes
The Virginia Academy of Science Archives includes VAS publications dating from 1939-present.The VAS Archives also includes manuscript and published versions of various Academy histories.The Academy Archives also includes correspondence, report, and minutes of section and of ad hoc and standing committees, annual financial statements, photographs and clippings, by-laws, and constitutions, records of special projects such as the visiting scientists program (supported by National Science Foundation grants), the Virginia Institute for Scientific Research and the Virginia Museum of Science.
Virginia Academy of Science (VAS).
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
The Virginia Academy of Science Archives deposited in Special Collections are largely the result of the preservation of the records by the individual officers, section heads, and committee chairs. Throughout the Academy’s history these records have been stored in various places around the state. Their being brought together in 1981 in one location is largely the work of the VAS Archives Committee under the leadership of Dr. Boyd Harshbarger. Donations have been made continuously since that time by the Academy and individual members.
Additional donations are expected in the future.
Historical Note
In 1923, one hundred and thirty-five scientists chartered the Virginia Academy of Science (VAS) and held their first annual VAS meeting in Williamsburg on April 26th. The Academy has continued to meet annually since then (except during World War II), bringing together scientists from every field throughout the state. The records of the Virginia Academy of Science have been arranged in chronological order by year, then by those principal officers who maintained large quantities of records, and by the scientific sections and committees whose records have survived.
The early records of the Academy can be attributed largely to the efforts of E. C. L. Miller who was the only officer (secretary and treasurer) to serve continuously, 1924-1949. During these years, he corresponded widely for the entire Academy, maintained committee reports, compiled the yearly programs, and saw that formal records were published annually in the Proceedings. The strength of the VAS Archives lies largely in the historic intuition of such officers, section heads, or committee chairs who maintained the files. Some files are much more complete than others. The early records of the Research Committee, for example, contain applications, papers submitted for consideration for the annual award, and records of the efforts of J. Shelton Horsley to raise an endowment to support these awards which were later named in his honor. More recent files are limited to minutes and annual reports. The Geology Section has perhaps the most complete set of records of section activities, especially during the leadership of William M. McGill. The activities of other committees and sections are often preserved in the Council’s records, however, while the Proceedings through 1966 and/or the annual meeting files often contain reports of committees and sections.
Scope and Content
The Virginia Academy of Science Archives includes VAS publications dating from 1939-present. These include such in-house works as Review of the First Ten Years of the Research Committee (1939) and Announcement and a Challenge (1946?) as well as the Future ( 1950). The Academy has also published periodicals throughout its history. Claytonia was the first VAS journal (1934-39), followed by the Virginia Journal of Science (1940-43) and the Virginia Journal of Science, New Series (1950-present) (VJS). The Journal often focuses on special topics such as the issue which was devoted to the 1964 Virginia Symposium on Human Resources (held during the annual VAS conference); "Early Virginia," articles on scientific and cultural development in Virginia, was especially reprinted for the 350th anniversary of the founding of Jamestown in 1957; and in 1969 the VJS carried a series of articles on Virginia’s Dismal Swamp area. The Publications Committee records show that the Dismal Swamp series was the culmination of the work of many Academy members who had originally hoped for a separate work to be published like the James River Basin study. The Flora Committee of the Botany Section also periodically publishes a newsletter which became known as Jeffersonia in 1980; the Archives contain only scattered issues (11) from 1969-70, 1980. The Academy Archives also has copies of directories, brochures, and membership fliers which the VAS has published since about 1946.
The VAS Archives also includes manuscript and published versions of various Academy histories; especially interesting are the early versions by Ivey Foreman Lewis (first VAS president) and E. C. L. Miller. The Academy Archives contains quite extensive records of the work of Isabel Boggs and George Jeffers to coordinate the efforts of members to record the Academy’s past as well as the resulting master’s thesis of Harry J. Staggers, History of the Virginia Academy of Science, 1925-1927 (College of William and Mary, 1966). This history of the VAS appeared in the Winter 1968 issue of the Virginia Journal of Science and in Spring 1973 the Journal carried the more recent VAS history, 1948-1972, to commemorate the fiftieth anniversary of the Virginia Academy of Science charter.
The Academy Archives also includes correspondence, report, and minutes of section and of ad hoc and standing committees, annual financial statements, photographs and clippings, by-laws, and constitutions, records of special projects such as the visiting scientists program (supported by National Science Foundation grants), the Virginia Institute for Scientific Research and the Virginia Museum of Science.
Arrangement
Boxes 1-20 are arranged chronologically by subject files. Boxes 26 and 28-36 contain VAS papers arranged chronologically by creator/collector. Boxes 37-38 are arranged by material type.
Boxes 21-25, 27, and 39-40 contain publications arranged chronologically by title.
Boxes 41-43 are in their original order.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Virginia Academy of Science (VAS).; Virginia. Junior Academy of Sciences.
Subjects:
Science and Technology
Contents List
- Box 1, 1920-1938 (Box 1)
  - Association of Virginia Biologists--Correspondence, Minutes, and Membership--Donald W. Davis, Secretary and Ivey Lewis, 1920-1921
  - Association of Virginia Biologists--Correspondence--Ivey Lewis, 1920-1924
  - Constitution, 1923
  - Membership and list of charter members, 1923
  - E. C. L. Miller --Correspondence, 1923
  - Ivey Lewis--Correspondence, 1924
  - Membership, 1924
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1925
  - Ivey Lewis--Correspondence, 1925
  - Membership, includes photograph and identification from the 1970s, 1925
  - Shelton J. Horsley--Correspondence, 1926
  - Ivey Lewis--Correspondence, 1926
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1926
  - Research Committee--Correspondence--Miller, 1926
  - Report of the Research Committee, 1926
  - Shelton J. Horsley--Correspondence, 1927
  - Ivey Lewis--Correspondence, 1927
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1927
  - Certificate of Incorporation, 1927
  - Research Committee--Correspondence--Oliver, 1927
  - Report of the Committee on the Design of the Seal, 1928
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1928
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence--Miller and First & Merchants National Bank, Richmond, 1928
  - Officer's Reports, 1928
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1928-1929
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1929
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence, 1929
  - Geology Section--Minutes--William M. McGill, 1929
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, Applications, and Minutes, 1929
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1929-1930
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1930
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence, 1930
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Program, Minutes, and Members--William M. McGill, 1930
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Minutes, 1930
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1930-1931
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1931
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence--First & Merchants National Bank, 1931
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Program, Minutes, and Members--William M. McGill, 1931
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, Applications, and Minutes, 1931
  - Reprint--J. C. Forbes, 1931
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1931-1932
  - Officer’s Reports, 1931-1932
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1932
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence, 1932
  - Geology Section--Correspondence and Minutes--William M. McGill, 1932
  - Research Committee--Minutes, 1932
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1932
  - Reprint--John H. Yoe, 1932
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1932-1933
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1933
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence, 1933
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Program, and Minutes--McGill and Roberts, 1933
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, Applications, and Minutes, 1933
  - State Museum Committee--Correspondence--G. W. Jeffers, 1933
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1933-1934
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1934
  - Endowment Fund--Correspondence, 1934
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Program, and Minutes--McGill, 1934
  - Membership, 1934
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, Applications, and Minutes, 1934
  - Reprints--J. C. Forbes and E. C. Cocke, 1934
  - State Museum Committee--Correspondence--G. W. Jeffers, 1934
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1934-1935
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1935
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Members, and Program--McGill, 1935
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1935
  - Reprint--T. W. Turner, 1935
  - State Museum Committee--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1935
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1935-1936
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1936
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1936
  - History of the American Association for the Advancement of Science--F. R. Mouton, 1936?
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1936?
  - Paper--M. J. Murray, 1936?
  - State Museum Committee--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1936?
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1936-1937
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1937
  - First & Merchants National Bank and Miller--Correspondence, 1937
  - Miller and Horsley--Correspondence, 1937
  - Endowment Fund Campaign--Correspondence--J. Shelton Horsley, 1937
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1937
  - Geology Section--Program and Attendance, 1937
  - Local Arrangements Committee--Correspondence and Press Releases, 1937
  - Reprint--A. C. Delisle, W. B. Gurley, and G. Van Huysen, 1937
  - State Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1937
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1937-1938
  - First & Merchants National Bank and Miller--Correspondence, 1938
  - Miller--Correspondence, 1938
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1938
  - Geology Section--Minutes, Programs, and Membership, 1938
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1938
  - Science Education--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1938
- Box 2, 1938-1943 (Box 2)
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchants National Bank, 1938-1939
  - First & Merchants National Bank and Miller--Correspondence, 1939
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1939
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science clippings, 1939
  - Constitution and by-laws, 1939
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--William M. McGill, 1939
  - Geology Section--Minutes, Program and Members, 1939
  - Review of the First Ten Years of the Research Committee, 1929-38, also includes review of the paper, 1939
  - Research Committee Awards Survey--Correspondence--Summary of the Winners from 1929-1938, 1939
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1939
  - Reprint--A. L. Delisle, 1939
  - Science Education--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1939
  - State Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1939
  - Photograph of June 9, 1939 Annual Meeting of VAS, 1939
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchant National Bank, 1939-1940
  - First & Merchants National Bank and Miller--Correspondence, 1940
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1940
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--William M. McGill, 1940
  - Geology Section--Minutes, 1940
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1940
  - Reprint--W. B. Gurley and G. Van Huysen, 1940
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchant National Bank, 1940-1941
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1941
  - Education and Publicity Subcommittee Report--Goal of VAS, 1941
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1941
  - Geology Section--Minutes, Programs, and Members, 1941
  - History of Science in the South--Virginia Institute of Science Research, 1941
  - James River Project--Legislation, 1941
  - James River Project--Report, 1941
  - Long Range Planning Committee--Correspondence and Minutes, 1941
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Minutes, 1941
  - Research Committee--Survey of Awards: 1929-1941 and Minutes, 1941
  - Reprint--M. Altmann, E. Knowles, and H. D. Bull, 1941
  - Paper--A. F. Meyer, E. C. Cocke, H. F. Eich, and P. H. McGauhey, 1941
  - Southern Association of Science and Industry--Jeffers, 1941
  - State Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1941
  - Statement of Account, 1941-1942
  - A State Academy Charts its Course--Jeffers, 1941-1942
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1942
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1942
  - Geology Section--Minutes and Members, 1942
  - Research Committee--Correspondence--About its history, 1942
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1942
  - Research Committee--Minutes--Haag, 1942
  - Southern Association of Science and Industry--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1942
  - State of Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1942
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Legislation, 1942
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchant National Bank, 1942-1943
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1943
  - Annual Meeting--Program, 1943
  - Geology Section--Correspondence and Minutes--Bloomer, 1943
  - Research Committee--Correspondence and Applications, 1943
  - Research Committee--Minutes, 1943
  - Southern Association of Science--Correspondence and Reports--Jeffers, 1943
  - Statistics Section--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1943
  - State Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1943
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Legislation, 1943
- Box 3, 1944-1950 (Box 3)
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1944
  - R. F. Smart--President’s Message, 1944
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Minutes, and Program, 1944
  - Statistics Section--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1944
  - State Museum of Science--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1944
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Legislation, 1944
  - President’s Message--H. Rupert Hammer (?), 1945
  - E. C. L. Miller--Correspondence, 1945-1946
  - L. C. Bird--Correspondence, 1945-1946
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1945-1946
  - Geology Section--Program, 1945-1946
  - Southern Association of Science & Industry--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1945-1946
  - Statistics Section--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1945-1946
  - A. S. Bevan and Miller--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - An Announcement and a Challenge--Virginia Junior Academy of Science, 1946-1947
  - Conservation Education Committee--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Exchange of Students Committee--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Finance and Endowment Committee--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Minutes, and Members--McGill, 1946-1947
  - Membership Committee--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Planning Committee--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1946-1947
  - Southern Association of Science & Industry--Correspondence and Report, 1946-1947
  - Statistics Section--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1946-1947
  - Virginia Science Talent Search--Correspondence, 1946-1947
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1947-1948
  - James River Project--Correspondence, 1947-1948
  - James River Project--Reports, 1947-1948
  - Local Arrangements Committee--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1947-1948
  - List of membership, 1947-1948
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1947-1948
  - Statistics Section--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1947-1948
  - Statistics Section--Papers, 1947-1948
  - Boyd Harshbarger--Correspondence--President-elect, 1948-1949
  - Council--Correspondence, 1948-1949
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1948-1949
  - James River Project--Reports, 1948-1949
  - Long Range Planning Committee--Correspondence and Survey, 1948-1949
  - Science Education--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1948-1949
  - Science Museum of Virginia--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1948-1949
  - Science Talent Search--Correspondence, 1948-1949
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1948-1949
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Report, 1948-1949
  - Financial Statements--Report--J. Waddell Rison, Accountant, 1949-1950
  - Statement of Account--First & Merchant National Bank, 1949-1950
  - L. C. Bird--Correspondence, 1949-1950
  - C. M. Goethe--Correspondence, 1949-1950
  - B. Harshbarger--Correspondence--Includes presidential address, 1949-1950
  - Lane Company--Correspondence, 1949-1950
  - F. Smith, Secretary--Correspondence, 1949-1950
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science-Correspondence and Reports, 1949-1950
  - Constitution and By-laws, 1949-1950
  - Council--Minutes, 1949-1950
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--McGill, 1949-1950
  - Geology Section--Program and Members, 1949-1950
- Box 4, 1949-1976 (Box 4)
  - James River Project--Correspondence and Reports, 1949-1950
  - Proceedings--Correspondence--Harshbarger and F. Smith, 1949-1950
  - Proceedings--Drafts, 1949-1950
  - Program, 1949-1950
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Harshbarger, Hobbs, Flory, Baugh, Negus, and F. Smith, 1949-1950
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Editor's meeting and material for publication, 1949-1950
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Financial Support, Pledges, Subscriptions, General papers and abstracts, Papers, abstracts, press copies, Statistics Section, and Printing (Radford News Journal), 1949-1950
  - Committee Appointments--Correspondence, 1950-1951
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1950-1951
  - Academy Conference/AAAS--Reports, 1950-1951
  - Academy Conference--Correspondence--Harshbarger and other state academies, 1950-1951
  - Financial Statement--Report--J. Waddell Rison, 1950-1951
  - Finance and Endowment Committee--Correspondence, 1950-1951
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, 1950-1951
  - James River Project--Reprint--Negus and Sidney, 1950-1951
  - Research Committee--Papers--Horsley competition, 1950-1951
  - Science Teaching--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1950-1951
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Harshbarger, Hobbs, Horlsey, Baugh, Negus, and F. Smith, 1950-1951
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Subscriptions, 1950-1951
  - Financial Statement--Report--J. Waddell Rison, CPA, 1951-1952
  - American Association for the Advancement of Science--Correspondence, 1951-1952
  - Academy Conference/AAAS--Reports, 1951-1952
  - Council--Minutes, 1951-1952
  - Dismal Swamp--Report, 1951-1952
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, 1951-1952
  - Research Committee--Paper--Bradley & Terry and D. R. H. Gourley, 1951-1952
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Harshbarger, Baugh, Husted, Negus, Coe, Stow, Horsley, Bird, Patterson, and Hobbs. Also includes subscriptions, 1951-1952
  - Academy Conference--History--1926-1952, 1952-1953
  - Council--Minutes, 1952-1953
  - Finance Committee--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1952-1953
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Program, and Members, 1952-1953
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1952-1953
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence--Harshbarger, Baber, Baugh, Bird, Stow, Hobbs, and F. Smith, 1952-1953
  - Dismal Swamp Project, 1952-1976
- Box 5, 1953-1969 (Box 5)
  - Miscellaneous--Correspondence, 1953-1954
  - Council--Minutes, 1953-1954
  - Dismal Swamp--Correspondence--UVa Press, 1953-1954
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Minutes, and Members, 1953-1954
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence, 1953-1954
  - Geology Section--Correspondence--Spring Field Conference, 1954-1955
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1954-1955
  - Science Education Committee--Correspondence--Jeffers, 1954-1955
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Report--Harshbarger, 1954-1955
  - Minutes of Biology Section, 1954-1976
  - Financial Statement--Report--J. Waddell Rison, 1955
  - Miscellaneous--Correspondence and Program, 1955-1956
  - Awards Committee--Correspondence--Harshbarger, 1955-1956
  - Council--Minutes, 1955-1956
  - Finance Committee--Correspondence and Minutes, 1955-1956
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Geology Section--Guidebook--Field Trip, 1955-1956
  - Place of Meeting Committee--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Science Education Committee--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Science Talent Search--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Correspondence, 1955-1956
  - Financial Statement--Report--J. Waddell Rison & Co., 1 January 1956-31 December 1957, 1956-1957
  - Miscellaneous--Correspondence, 1956-1957
  - Lists of committees, section heads, and officers, 1956-1957
  - Council--Correspondence--Committees and officers, 1956-1957
  - Dismal Swamp Geology--Correspondence--M. Stow, 1956-1957
  - Long Range Planning Committee--Correspondence, 1956-1957
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1956-1957
  - Science Education--Reports--Jeffers and others, 1956-1957
  - Rodney C. Berry--Correspondence, 1957-1958
  - Council--Minutes, 1957-1958
  - Finance and Endowment Committee--Correspondence--Includes committee to secure funds for research., 1957-1958
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, Minutes, Program, and Members, 1957-1958
  - Geology Section--Road Log--Field Trip, 1957-1958
  - Local Arrangements Committee--Correspondence, 1957-1958
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1957-1958
  - Virginia Institute for Scientific Research--Report--Gwathmey(?), 1957-1958
  - History of Academies in America--Report--C. L. Baker, 1957-1958
  - Financial Statement--Report--J. Waddell Rison & Co., 1958
  - Officers and Committees, 1958-1959
  - Harshbarger--Correspondence--Various committees, 1958-1959
  - Agricultural Science Section--Correspondence, 1958-1959
  - Council--Minutes, 1958-1959
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, 1958-1959
  - Geology Section--Itinerary--Field Trip, 1958-1959
  - History of Science in Virginia Committee--Correspondence, 1958-1959
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1958-1959
  - Science Education, 1958-1959
  - Agricultural Science Section--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Annual Meeting--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Council--Minutes, 1959-1960
  - Finance and Endowment Committee--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Geology Section--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Geology Section--Itinerary-Field Trip, 1959-1960
  - Goethe and Horsley Awards--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Research Committee--Correspondence, 1959-1960
  - Virginia Journal of Science--Report--Financial, 1959-1960